Guide to the Arts and Sciences Council Records, 1991 - 1999 UA.28.01.0006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arts and Sciences Council records
1991 - 1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Arts and Sciences Council
UA.28.01.0006
3.5 Linear Feet
The Arts and Sciences Council was established at Duke University in July 1991, when the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences disbanded and reconstituted itself to include some aspects of graduate studies and research initiatives. The Arts and Sciences Council is elected by the Arts and Sciences faculty and serves as this faculty's primary institution for faculty governance. The Council also determines and implements the broad objectives of undergraduate education and considers all matters affecting the academic and residential environments of students, making recommendations and adopting regulations where appropriate. Records include correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, questionnaires, and other materials documenting the activities of the A & S Council. The bulk of the materials were generated by the Curriculum Review Committee, circa 1992-1999. The collection also features records created by several other committees, including Academic Affairs, Academic Standards, Financial Aid, Residential Life, and Senior Year. English.
3000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Arts and Sciences Council Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1993-2001.
Historical Note
The Arts and Sciences Council (A & S Council) was established 1 July 1991, when the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS) disbanded and reconstituted itself; the Arts and Sciences Council first met on September 12, 1991. Its purposes include representing the faculty and advising the deans of Arts and Sciences with particular respect to Trinity College. The A & S Council retained UFCAS's functions, but added other matters to its purview, including some aspects of graduate studies and research initiatives. The Executive Committee of the Arts and Sciences Council established four ad hoc committees and recommended to Deans White and Gillis appointments to the following committees: Committee on Facilities, Committee to Review Study Abroad, Curriculum Review Committee, and the Committee on the Teaching of Korean Languages. Since 1991, some of these committees have been disbanded or re-organized, and new committees have been formed.
In 2005, the Arts and Sciences council provided the following description of its purpose on its website: "The Arts and Sciences Council is elected by the Arts and Sciences faculty and serves as this faculty's primary institution for faculty governance. The purposes of the Council are to represent the faculty and advise the Deans of Arts and Sciences and Trinity College with respect to: Arts and Sciences priorities; faculty development; support and policy for faculty research, teaching, and administrative facilities; organization of departments and units within the Arts and Sciences faculty; areas of interaction between graduate and undergraduate programs such as teaching assistantships, instructional budgets, and teacher training; and any other matters of particular concern to the Arts and Sciences faculty. With particular respect to Trinity College, the Council determines and implements the broad objectives of undergraduate education and considers all matters affecting the academic and residential environments of students, making recommendations and adopting regulations where appropriate. The Council meets monthly during the academic year."
Collection Overview
Arts and Sciences Council records include correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, questionnaires, and other materials documenting the activities of the A&S Council. The bulk of the materials were generated by the Curriculum Review Committee, circa 1992-1999. In 1992 Dean Richard White appointed the Curriculum Review Committee to evaluate the undergraduate curriculum. The records of the committee document its processes of studying the curriculum as well as its evaluation and recommendations. Surveys concerning the curriculum, which were completed by faculty as well as juniors and seniors are included. Curriculum issues reflected in the records include the Undergraduate Writing Course, requirements for academic majors, the division of the curriculum into six areas of knowledge, and academic advising. Copies of earlier curriculum studies, Structure and Choice in Liberal Education (1986) and A Climate for Liberal Learning (1980), are included.
The collection also features records created by several other committees, including Academic Affairs, Academic Standards, Financial Aid, Residential Life, and Senior Year.
Related Material
Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Undergraduate Faculty Council Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Education, Higher -- Aims and objectives; Education, Higher -- Curricula; Sound recordings; Duke University. Arts and Sciences Council; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences; Duke University. Arts and Sciences Council; Duke University -- Curricula; Duke University -- Administration
- Minutes, 1991-1999
  - Minutes, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1995-1999 (Box 5)
- Committees
  - Curriculum Review Committee (Box 2)
    - Bulletin (Box 2)
    - Minutes and memoranda, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum studies, 1980-1992 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous records, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire: Collation of responses, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire responses: Faculty, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire responses: Students, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences minutes, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire results, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Responses to CRC report, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Report drafts, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Audio tapes of committee meetings, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Senior Year Committee (Box 3)
  - Academic Affairs Committee: Writing Program review (Box 4)
  - Academic Standards Committee (Box 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Financial Aid (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Review Committee (Box 4)
  - Residential Life Committee (Box 4)
  - Senior Year Committee (Box 4)
  - TASC Planning and Priorities Committee (Box 4)